Finding Aid for Michigan Association of Speech Communication records, 1940-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Association of Speech Communication records 1940-1997, 1970-1990
Michigan Association of Speech Communication.
4 linear feet
85289 Bi 2
Originally an organization of speech teacher; minutes, financial reports, budgets, topical files on association activities, committee reports, conference journals, and membership directories published by the association.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was first deposited with the library in 1975. Periodic additions have been received (Donor No. 5757 ).
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
In 1925 twenty-nine speech teachers from around the state of Michigan gathered to discuss the viability of creating a professional organization to represent the various levels of their profession, ranging from elementary and high school teachers to instructors at the junior college, "normal" college and university levels. Thus was born the Michigan Association of Teachers of Speech. From these modest beginnings the association grew rapidly in membership, claiming 254 members by 1940 and reaching a peak of 460 members by 1968. In the period 1925-1950 the organization began a gradual expansion of its activities, and the scope of its influence on the profession, both within the state and nationally, increased concurrently. This rapid development was accomplished in part through affiliations with larger organizations such as the Central States Speech Association and the Speech Association of America (1932), the Michigan Schoolmaster's Club (1925), and the Michigan Education Association (1950).
The most significant contribution of the association during this era was the creation of its first curriculum guides in 1935. These guides, then called "Courses of Study," were designed to standardize the teaching of speech communication in the state and resulted from the findings of a "barnstorming" tour in which association members traveled to representative schools in the state to survey the condition of speech instruction. Their discovery that many speech teachers were "under-prepared" for their tasks resulted in the construction of these curriculum aids, which have undergone several revisions and are still published currently, providing a major source of income for the association.
The period 1950-1975 represents perhaps the "golden age" of the organization. This era was characterized by a steady increase in membership accompanied by recognition within the profession as perhaps the most influential and successful of all the state speech associations. The organization's first significant action during this era was changing its name to the Michigan Speech Association (MSA) in 1950. This new title was designed to reflect the increasing diversification of its activities and membership (student memberships were added at this time), and to safeguard its position on the "cutting edge" of the field. Some notable accomplishments of this period included the addition of new association publications, further revisions of the curriculum guide, establishment of independent conference programs, efforts at standardizing teacher certification requirements, and implementation of a job placement program. The publication of the Bulletin (the association newsletter) in 1949 and the Journal (a compendium of in-state scholarly articles in the area of speech communication) in 1966 represented perhaps the most important achievements of the time. Also, the constant battles over certification resulted in a 1968 requirement that speech teachers at the secondary level should have a B.A. in speech and an M.A. within the first five years of teaching, thus further enhancing the professional standards of the discipline. The establishment of annual conferences, independent from those of larger organizations such as the MEA, provided an influential forum for the discussion of new ideas, concepts, and research in the field, and opportunities to focus the membership on policy goals.
The years from 1975 to 1992 were marked by a creeping identity confusion both within the profession and the association itself. Membership dropped to a plateau of 200-250 members in the late 1970s. By the late 1980s membership had declined to less than 40% of the eligible professionals statewide. This substantial decrease in membership was accompanied by growing discord within the association as to whether the discipline should be taught as a liberal art, a social science, or as skill training. The field also experienced growing integration with related subject areas such as psychology, sociology, political science and communications. The increasing inter-disciplinary nature of undergraduate and graduate studies in speech was an outgrowth of decreasing funding of speech departments in the 1980s, as well as a reflection of current trends in the university community. The association's perception that its name had thus become outdated resulted in another change in 1983 to its current form, the Michigan Association of Speech Communication (MASC). With this name change the membership hoped to ally itself more closely with general communication studies to maintain the academic viability of the discipline.
The records of the Michigan Association of Speech Communication are comprised of documentation primarily generated by members of the organization's executive committee carrying out their functions as officers of this professional association. As such, the bulk of the materials are in the form of minutes, financial reports/budgets, topical files on various association activities, committee reports, conference planning material, and association publications such as newsletters and membership directories. Although the coverage of the materials spans the period 1940-1997, the majority of the records were produced between 1970 and 1990. The record group is arranged into five series: Administrative Materials, Executive Council, Printed Material, Conferences, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Communication--Study and teaching.; Michigan Association of Speech Communication.; Michigan Speech Association.
- Administrative Materials
  The Administrative Materials series includes reports, guides, topical files, financial material, and minutes of meetings (except for executive council).
  - Certification Standards and Accreditation (Box 1)
  - Committee reports, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conference programs, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conference evaluations, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Guides, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Distinguished Service Award and Life Membership (Box 1)
  - Financial statements: Budgets and treasurer's reports, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Golden Anniversary (Box 1)
  - Historical statements and surveys, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Education Association Affiliations, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Schoolmasters Club Affiliations (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Business meetings (Fall and Spring), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Officers' Reports (Box 1)
  - Placement Service (Box 1)
  - Silver Anniversary (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Summer Conference (Joint Sponsorship) (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed book: "A Research into the Teaching of Public Speaking" (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed book 1937: "The Science and Art of Speech-making" by John Merrill Heaphy (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed booklet 1942: "Three Centuries of Speech Teaching Experience" (Box 1)
  - 1980-1986 materials (unprocessed) (Box 2)
- Executive Council 1951-1990
  The Executive Council series is arranged into three subseries: (1) Executive Council Meeting Minutes (2) Financial Reports and Proposed Budgets and, (3) Committee Reports.
  The Executive Council Meeting Minutes subseries contains a fairly comprehensive accumulation of the minutes of the proceedings of Executive Council meetings between 1951-1955 and 1964-1990. These minutes provide insight into the reasons behind major policy decisions and the dynamics of the operation of the executive council. Also included, interspersed within the official minutes, are various committee reports (presented during executive council meetings) on such issues as curriculum guidelines, the condition of speech education in the state, certification standards, and research trends in the field. Other topics covered in the executive council minutes include constitutional revision efforts, standards for association publications, planning of annual conferences, financing of various operations, and membership drives.
  The Financial Reports and Proposed Budgets subseries provides summary information detailing the expenditures and debts of the organization during the period 1958-1990. As such, these records provide a clear indication of the scope and nature of the various activities, publications, conferences, etc., sponsored by the association.
  The Committee Reports subseries is comprised of reports filed separately from the Executive Council minutes which describe the findings and policy recommendations of the curriculum guide, research, and certification committees among others, from various periods between 1958 and 1969. Of note are the efforts outlined in the research committee reports to stimulate research in speech education on the topics which were in academic vogue during the era. Also, the reports of the certification committee for 1968-1969 contain information on the status of speech education in the state and recommendations for improving certification standards and criteria.
  - Executive Council Meeting Minutes
    - 1951-1955 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-March, 1971 (Box 2)
    - 4/1971-10/1971 (Box 3)
    - October, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987-April, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports and Proposed Budgets
    - 1958-1970 (Box 3)
    - 1971-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 3)
  - Committee Reports
    - Curriculum Guide Committee 1958-1967 (Box 3)
    - Research Committee 1964-1968 (Box 3)
    - Certification Committee 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Committee Reports 1967-1969 (Box 3)
- Printed Material 1949-1990
  The Printed Material series is arranged into three subseries: (1) MSA/MASC Bulletin (2) MSA/MASC Journal and, (3) MSA/MASC Directory and Constitution and Bylaws.
  The MSA/MASC Bulletin subseries contains various issues of this newsletter printed between 1961 and 1990. These publications represent an important source of information about the most significant events in the history of the association, its most influential figures, and important accomplishments of the group. This publication also serves as a valuable tool for the study of the general nature of speech education in the state through its regular inclusion of articles (included in the running sections of "On the Campus" and "High School Highlights") describing the activities of intermediate, high school, and college/university speech instruction programs. Other notable topics covered at different times in this newsletter include presidential messages, career information, the 1983 name change, focuses on the use of audio/visual materials in speech instruction, and issues of ethics in communication.
  The MSA/MASC Journal subseries contains copies of this scholarly journal sponsored by the association and printed between 1966 and 1997 (some volumes missing). The articles in the journal present an interesting illustration of the research trends which have characterized the discipline during this era. The studies described in these volumes show a clear evolution towards more quantitative social science research and a growing emphasis on the relation of the speech discipline to social psychology, political science, sociology, communications, and linguistics. Also of interest are articles exemplifying the growing influence of broadcast media analysis, gender-based and minority studies, and such post-modernist conceptions as "heuristics" appearing in journals from the mid-1970s to the present.
  The MSA/MASC Directory and Constitution and Bylaws series consists of annual published membership lists, constitutions and bylaws, and other information dating from 1965 to 1992 (various issues). These directories present a picture of the quantity, nature, experience/qualifications, and affiliations of the membership during the period. The issues after 1967-1968 also contain lists of past presidents, charter members, honorary lifetime members, regional representatives, executive council officers, and conference venues/dates.
  - MSA/MASC Bulletin
    - April 1949-March 1969 (various) (Box 3)
    - 1970-Winter 1982 (various) (Box 3)
    - Winter 1983-Fall 1990 (various) (Box 3)
  - MSA/MASC Journal
    - Vol. 1 (1966)-Vol. 5 (1970) (Box 3)
    - Vol. 6 (1971)-Vol. 9 (1974), Vol. 11 (1976) (Box 3)
    - Vol. 12 (1977)-Vol. 14 (1979) (Box 3)
    - Vol. 15 (1980)-Vol. 18 (1983) (Box 3)
    - Vol. 19 (1984)-Vol. 22 (1987) (Box 3)
    - Vol. 23 (1988)-Vol. 27 (1992) (Box 3)
    - Vol. 28 (1993)-Vol. 32 (1997) (Box 3)
  - MSA/MASC Directory and Constitution and Bylaws
    - 1940-1964 (Box 4)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 4)
    - 1970/71-1977/78 (Box 4)
    - 1981-1983, 1988, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
- Conferences
  The Conferences series is arranged into four subseries: (1) Conference Planning (2) Conference Programs (3) Summary of Evaluations and, (4) Communicator of the Year Award. The Conference Planning subseries consists of documentation resulting from the activities of association officers involved with planning the programs, workshops, lectures, and presentations which would be conducted during the semi-annual MASC conferences, 1982-1984 and 1986-1990. These materials are another valuable source for investigating the topics, research methodologies, and pedagogy which were popular in the profession at the time. Especially useful in this regard is correspondence from members suggesting to conference planners ideas for conference programs, activities, lectures, etc.
  The Conference Programs subseries contains copies of conference programs from the periods 1957-1967 and 1975-1991. These programs contribute a clear explanation of the activities, speakers, and topics which were slated for each conference, thus indicating the "final product" resulting from the activities documented in the Conference Planning subseries.
  The Summary of Evaluations subseries consists of reports quantifying and explaining (through surveys of participants) the reaction of members to the conference programs of 1968, 1985, and 1987. These summaries serve as another source to gauge the tenor of the membership's attitude towards the issues of the day in the field of speech communication.
  The Communicator of the Year Award subseries comprises two folders of records relating to the creation of the award and selection process/criteria for determining the recipients for 1987-1990. The records describe the intent of the award as an effort to publicize the importance of speech communication in society in a period of declining interest, and the winners include Lee Iacocca and Ernie Harwell.
  - Conference Planning
    - 1982 (Box 4)
    - 1983 (Box 4)
    - 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1986 (Box 4)
    - 1987 (Box 4)
    - 1988 (Box 4)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Conference Programs
    - 1957-1967 (various) (Box 4)
    - 1975-1984 (various) (Box 4)
    - 1985-1991 (various) (Box 4)
  - Summary of Evaluations
    - 1968 Conference (Box 4)
    - 1985 Conference (Box 4)
    - 1987 Conference (Box 4)
  - Communicator of the Year Award
    - 1987-1989 (Box 4)
    - 1990 (Box 4)
- Topical File
  The Topical Files series contains records generated out of various activities and affiliations of the MASC from the mid-1950s to the late 1980s. Of particular interest are materials relating to the MASC's cooperative projects with such larger organizations as the Michigan Education Association and the Central States Speech Association, records documenting efforts to modernize the constitution (and emphasize "communication" over "speech" in stating the purpose of the association) in the late 1980s, membership drive strategies, and the state-funded program of 1978-1981 which enlisted the MASC to measure the "speaking and listening" abilities of fourth, seventh and tenth grade students.
  - Central States Speech Association, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Certification circa 1958-1969 (Box 4)
  - Constitutional Revision 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Guide 1964 (Box 4)
  - ERIC-Speech Communication Module (Box 4)
  - Job Descriptions (Box 4)
  - Literacy Consortium (Box 4)
  - Membership Drives 1969-1983 (Box 4)
  - Membership Lists and Constitution and Bylaws 1959-1965, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Education Association Affiliation (Box 4)
  - Michigan High School Forensics Association (Box 4)
  - MSA Archives (Box 4)
  - MSA Goals Task Force (Box 4)
  - MSA Journal (Box 4)
  - Rhodes, Stephen (President, 1981-1983) Notebook (Box 4)
  - State Fund Project (Box 4)